A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Director, Simon Flexner, Biographical Materials, Reprints, Phonorecords, and Bas Relief, Series 6 FA139
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Director, Simon Flexner, Biographical Materials, Reprints, Phonorecords, and Bas Relief, Series 6
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Flexner, Simon
FA139
2.96 Cubic Feet
1 box, 1 volume
Biographical/Historical note
Simon Flexner (1863-1946) pathologist, Director of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research from its founding in 1903 until 1935; Emeritus until his death in 1946. Writer of numerous papers and monographs on pathological and bacteriological subjects. Investigated especially the pathology of toxalbumin intoxication, biochemical constitution of snake venoms, experimental pancreatitis and fat necrosis; epidemic cerebrospinal meningitis and its serum treatment; poliomyelitis, its cause and mode of transmission, serum treatment; experimental epidemiology; epidemic encephalitis.
Biographical Note
1863 Born March 25, Louisville, Ky.; Attended Louisville public schools
1889 M.D. University of Louisville
1891-1895 Post Graduate student, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore; Fellow in pathology, Johns Hopkins University; Associate in Pathology, Johns Hopkins University
1893 Post graduate student, University of Strasburg; Post graduate student, University of Prague
1895-1898 Associate Professor Pathology, Johns Hopkins University
1898-1899 Professor of pathological anatomy, Johns Hopkins University
1899-1903 Professor of Pathology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia
1900 Post graduate student, Pasteur Institute
1900-1903 Pathologist, University Hospital and Philadelphia Hospital, Philadelphia
1901-1903 Director, Ayer Clinical Laboratories, Pennsylvania Hospital, Philadelphia
1903-1935 Director, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York, N.Y.
1904 Post graduate student, University of Berlin
1935 Director Emeritus, RIMR
1937-1938 Eastman Professor, Oxford University
1946 Died May 2, New York, New York
Awards
1911 Cameron Prize (England)
1915 Order of the Sacred Treasure, Japan
1914 Legion of Honor, France. Chevalier
1919 Legion of Honor, France. Officier
1923 Legion of Honor, France. Commandeur
Served
1899 Johns Hopkins University Commission to Philippine Islands. Chairman
1900 U.S. Plague Commission. Chairman
1905-1946 Editor: Journal of Experimental Medicine
1917-1919 Lt. Colonel O.R.C. United States Army
1919 Colonel O.R.C United States Army
1919 Assistant Surgeon General. United States Public Health Service
1919 Congress of American Physicians and Surgeons
1919 Congress of the American Association for the Advancement of Science
1919 The Rockefeller Foundation. Charter Member
1919 Chinese Medical Board Commission
1919 American Red Cross. Medical Advisory Committee
1919 Carnegie Foundation. Trustee
1919 National Research Council. Chairman Fellowship Board: Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics
1937 Johns Hopkins University Trustee
Honorary Degrees D.SC. 1906 Harvard University, 1910 Yale University, 1913 Princeton University, 1929 University of Pennsylvania, 1936 National University of Ireland, 1937 University of Louisville, LL.D. 1907 University of Maryland, 1915 Brown University, 1915 Johns Hopkins University, 1915 Washington University, 1920 Cambridge University, England, 1929 Western Reserve University, Doctor Honorarius 1923 University of Strasburg, France, 1927 Catholic University of Louvain, Belgium, 1930 Université Libre, Brussels, 1937 Fellow of Balliol College, Master of Arts, Oxford University
Member of American Academy of Arts and Sciences (Fellow), New York Academy of Medicine (Fellow), American Association for the Advancement of Sciences, National Academy of Sciences, Association of American Physicians (Pres. 1914), American Philosophical Society, American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists, American Medical Association, Sigma Xi (Pennsylvania Chapter 1900), Harvey Society, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, Institute of Medicine, Chicago
Foreign Societies Membership British Medical Association, Royal Society of London, Royal Society of Medicine, London, Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene, London, Academy of Medicine, Paris, National Academy of Sciences, Paris, Société médicale des Hôpitaux, Paris, Société de Pathologie Exotique, Paris, Société de Biologie, Paris, Royal Academy of Medicine, Brussels, Société Royale des Sciences Médicales et Naturelles, Brussels, Société Belge de Médecine Tropicale, Société Belge de Biologie, Brussels, Institute for Experimental Therapy, Frankfurt a. M., Kaiserlich Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher zu Halle, Germany, Berliner medizinische Gesellschaft, Berlin, Gesellschaft de Aerzte in Wien, Austria, Wiener Gesellschaft für Mikrobiologie, Austria, Reale Istituto Lombardo di Scienze e Lettere, Milan, Medico-Chirugical Society, Bologna, Royal Danish Scientific Society, Swedish Medical Society, Stockholm, Copenhagen Medical Society, Bataafsch Genootschap der Proefondervindelijke Wijsbegeerte, Rotterdam, Microbiological Society in Leningrad, Russia, Sociedad Argentina de Biologia, Buenos Aires, Academy of Medicine, Caracas, Venezuela, Sociedad Medico-Quirurgica del Guayas, Guayaquil, Ecuador, Medical Advisory Board, League of Red Cross Societies, Geneva
Scope and Contents note
Biographical material, articles, photographs, obituary articles, family correspondence.
Related Materials
SImon Flexner papers at the American Philosophical Society Library.
Rockefeller Archive Center has a complete microfilm set of the Flexner papers. Microfilm is available upon request. Consult Archivist for details.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 301-6
Arrangement
As received.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Medical research; Medical sciences; Biology -- Research; Medicine, Preventive; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biochemistry; Pancreatitis; Meningitis; Epidemiology; Bacteria; Bacteriology
- Biographical materials
  - Obituary notices of Fellows of the Royal Society v. 6, 1949 November (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes bibliography.
  - Memorial meeting for Simon Flexner. Speakers: Herbert S. Gasser; Learned Hand; Peyton Rous, Raymond S. Fosdick; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (Typescript copy of all addresses except Dr. Gasser's), 1946 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Archives of pathology 42 (1946) 234-242 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - SCIENCE 107 (1948) 611-613 "Simon Flexner and Medical Discovery" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - BULLETIN de l'Académie de Médecine by M.G. Ramon no. 24-25-26 (1946) 429 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - LA PRESSE MEDICALE, 1946 Juillet 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - YEARBOOK American Philosophical Society, 289-297, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - COMPTES RENDUS. Read by M. Cartan at Académie des sciences, 1946 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bordet, Paul. Notice sur la vie et les travaux de Simon Flexner1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sketch by H. Gasser for Association of American Physicians (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notice released to press from RIMR 2, 1946 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical note edited by H. Gasser (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographic prints. Largely of Simon Flexner and family members (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes copy prints made from his personal collection of famous scientists, i.e. Alexis St. Marlin; Wm. Osler; S. Weir Mitchell; Billings; Victor Vaughan. Many others not identified. Some photos of items from personal collection from Peking Medical College.
    - Print of drawing made by Max Broedel of Simon Flexner and Lewellys F. Barker, 1896 in Johns Hopkins Hospital staff room
    - Drawing signed T.M. Rivers, 1926
- Copies of statistical material, correspondence and handwritten notes with material brought together for report of First 20 years of RIMR (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memoir book of Dinner in Honor of Simon Flexner on 10th Anniversary of opening of the laboratories. Delmonicos, 1914 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Reminiscences of Abraham Flexner and other articles (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Flexner, Abraham. Oral interview. Transcript Interview by Allan Nevins and Saul Benison for Oral History Research Office, Columbia University. 36pp with index, 1954
- Pamphlet: The New York Academy of Medicine PASTEUR CENTENARY. Catalogue of Exhibit p. 27 Simon Flexner "The contribution of Pasteur to the knowledge of immunity and therapy" (also p. 19 by William Welch), 1922 December 27-1923 January 10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Benison, Saul. "Poliomyelitis and The Rockefeller Institute: Social effects and Institutional response" Photocopy. JOURNAL OF HISTORY OF MEDICINE AND ALLIED SCIENCES, 74-92, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Benison, Saul. "Speculation and experimentation in early poliomyelitis research". CLIO MEDICA, 1-22, 1975 April 10 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Flexner Family. Papers, 1910-1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence with Abraham Flexner; James Flexner in deeding Simon Flexner papers to RIMR; a few items about various family members; material dealing with 1935 Simon Flexner medallion and Memorial pamphlet, 1946.
- Abraham Flexner: an autobiography. A revision, brought up to date, of the author's "I remember", published in 1940. Intro, by Allan Nevins. New York, Simon and Schuster, 1960. 302pp., 1 volume (Box 2)
- Ward, Patricia Spain, "The Other Abraham: Flexner in Illinois." Caduceus 2 (Spring 1986) pp 1-66 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes a 1923 photograph of Abraham Flexner from RU Archives opposite page 1. 2 copies of publication.
- Looseleaf notebook (with copies of memoranda, budget material, and blueprint for Princeton site), 1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Collected reprints
  Collected papers of Simon Flexner bound in 5 volumes:
  1 1890-1898.
  2 1899-1907.
  3 1907-1915.
  4 1916-1926.
  5 1927-1948.
- Reprints of Simon Flexner at RU - folio room
  - "The pathologic changes caused by certain so-called toxalbumins - an experimental study" Transactions of the Pathological Society of Philadelphia. 17: 212-31, 1896; Photocopies (Envelope 1)
  - Reprints
    Custodial History
    Given to RU by Eric Meyerhoff, Librarian of Cornell University Medical College, July 1984.
    - 1892-1898 (Envelope 2)
    - 1900-1909 (Envelope 3)
    - 1910-1917,1923, 1928, undated (Envelope 4)
- Phonorecords, Recordings: Retirement of Simon Flexner, 1935 October 7; 2 sets of 3 records each
  Conditions Governing Access
  RAC may be unable to provide access to the original item, depending on the condition of the recordings and due to the specialized equipment necessary to facilitate playback.
  Electrical transcription made by Airtone Recording Studio, 485 Madison Avenue, New York City.
- Bas relief of Simon Flexner, 1 box (2 1/2 inches) (Package 1)
  Bas relief of Simon Flexner. Sculpture by Bashka Paeff. Original is in marble (hangs in Rockefeller University Library).
  - Sculpture by Bashka Paeff
    - Marble, Original is in marble.
    - Bronze 6" x 8" with a stand was originally prepared for the laboratories at Princeton
    - Bronze 2 1/2" x 3" medallion
      On reverse addition was made of representation of The Rockefeller Institute from 66th Street gates and legend: From the Members of The Rockefeller Institute, 1935. These were made available for purchase on Simon Flexner's retirement.
  - Letter from Bashka Paeff Waxman, 1977 March